<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<MyCoReWebPage class="home" xmlns:i="http://www.mycore.org/i18n">
  <section xml:lang="all" title="DuEPublico: Textnachlass Germaine Krull">

    <div class="card-deck mt-3 mb-4">
      <div class="card">
        <div class="card-header">
          <h2>
            <i:de>Textnachlass Germaine Krull</i:de>
            <i:en>Estate Germaine Krull</i:en>
          </h2>
        </div>
        <div class="card-body">
          <img src="../../images/folkwang_krull2_alle_rechte_vorbehalten.jpg" class="float-right ml-3"
            style="width:250px" alt="Bild Germaine Krull. Alle Rechte vorbehalten" />
          <p class="card-text">
            <i:de>Der Nachlass Germaine Krulls, seit 1995 am Museum Folkwang, Essen, umfasst neben Fotografien,
              Negativen und Dokumenten auch Briefe und Manuskripte. Diese liegen zumeist in Form von Typoskripten vor.
            </i:de>
            <i:en>The Germaine Krull estate, which has been held at the Museum Folkwang in Essen since 1995, includes
              photographs, negatives and documents as well as letters and manuscripts. Most of these are in the form of
              typescripts.
            </i:en>
          </p>
          <p class="card-text">
            <i:de>Ein Teil der autobiografischen Schriften war mit der Nachlass-Übernahme als Kopie in den Nachlass
              Germaine Krulls integriert; Originale und überarbeitete Textfassungen verblieben weiterhin bei Christel
              Klose, der Germaine Krull die Rechte an diesem Teil ihres Werks vererbt hatte und die den gesamten
              Nachlass innerhalb der von ihr gegründeten „Germaine Krull Stiftung“. Jene Manuskripte gingen gemeinsam
              mit den Rechten am autobiografischen Werk nach Kloses Tod an deren Neffen Martin Lüpkes über. Dieser
              stellte sie im Jahr 2024 dem Museum Folkwang zur Sichtung, zum Abgleich und zur Verwendung zur Verfügung.
              Diese Zuordnungen sind jeweils ausgewiesen.
            </i:de>
            <i:en>Some of the autobiographical writings were included as copies in Germaine Krull's estate when it was
              transferred; the originals and revised versions of the texts remained with Christel Klose, to whom
              Germaine
              Krull had bequeathed the rights to this part of her work and who held the entire estate within the
              Germaine Krull Foundation she had established. After Klose's death, these manuscripts, together with the
              rights to the autobiographical work, passed to her nephew Martin Lüpkes. In 2024, he made them available
              to the Museum Folkwang for inspection, comparison and use. These assignments are indicated in each case.
            </i:en>
          </p>
          <p class="card-text">
            <a href="https://www.museum-folkwang.de/de/ausstellung/germaine-krull-chien-fou" target="_blank"
              title="Ausstellung im Museum Folkwang">
              <h6>
                <i:de>Zur Webseite der Ausstellung</i:de>
                <i:en>Visit the exhibition website</i:en>
              </h6>
            </a>
          </p>
          <p class="card-text">
            <a href="https://duepublico2.uni-due.de/receive/duepublico_mods_00084160" target="_blank">
              <h6>
                <i:de>Zum Textnachlass in DuEPublico</i:de>
                <i:en>To the estate in DuEPublico</i:en>
              </h6>
            </a>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div class="card-footer">
          <form class="rssfeed-search form-inline" method="post"
            action="https://duepublico2.uni-due.de/servlets/solr/select" role="search">
            <input value="root:duepublico_mods_00084160" name="q" type="hidden" />
            <div style="width:60%;" class="input-group">
              <label for="qSeries" class="sr-only input-group-prepend">Suche im Nachlass Germaine Krull</label>
              <input placeholder="Suche im Nachlass Germaine Krull" class="form-control" name="fq" type="text"
                id="qSeries" />
              <div class="input-group-append">
                <button type="submit" class="btn btn-primary">
                  <i class="fas fa-search"></i>
                </button>
              </div>
            </div>
          </form>

        </div>
      </div>
    </div>


    <div class="accordion" role="tablist" aria-multiselectable="true">
      <a name="vita"></a>

      <div class="card">
        <div class="card-header" role="tab" id="headingOne">
          <h5 class="card-title with-icon">
            <a role="button" data-toggle="collapse" data-parent=".accordion" href="#collapseOne" aria-expanded="false"
              aria-controls="collapseOne">
              <i:de>Biographische Eckpunkte</i:de>
              <i:en>Biographical milestones</i:en>
            </a>
          </h5>
        </div>
        <div id="collapseOne" class="card-collapse collapse out" role="tabcard" aria-labelledby="headingOne">
          <div class="card-body">
            <img src="../../images/folkwang_krull3_alle_rechte_vorbehalten.jpg" class="float-right ml-5"
              style="width:200px" alt="Bild Germaine Krull" />
            <p>
              <i:de>
                Zusammengestellt von
                <a href="https://duepublico2.uni-due.de/go/GKMA/impressum.xml#kontakt" target="_blank">Kerstin Meincke und Petra Steinhardt</a>
                (Juni 2025)
              </i:de>
              <i:en>
                Compiled by
                <a href="https://duepublico2.uni-due.de/go/GKMA/impressum.xml?lang=en#contact" target="_blank">Kerstin Meincke and Petra Steinhardt</a>
                (June 2025)
              </i:en>
            </p>
            <p>
              <i:de>1897 Geburt in Wilda, Poznán. Ihre Kindheit und Jugend verbringt Krull u.a. in Bosnien, Slowenien
                und Frankreich (Paris). 1906 Geburt der Schwester Berthe. 1912 Trennung der Eltern und Umzug nach
                München.
              </i:de>
              <i:en>1897 Born in Wilda, Poznań. Krull spends her childhood and youth in Bosnia, Slovenia and France
                (Paris), among other places. 1906 Birth of her sister Berthe. 1912 Separation of her parents and move to
                Munich.
              </i:en>
            </p>
            <p>
              <i:de>1915-17 Studium an der Lehr- und Versuchsanstalt für Photographie in München. Anschließend ebd. als
                Fotografin tätig; zeitweise ab 1918 mit eigenem Studio. Krull verkehrt in den intellektuellen Zirkeln um
                die Protagonist:innen und Unterstützer:innen der Münchner Räterepublik. 1917 verstirbt ihr Vater
                Friedrich Krull.
              </i:de>
              <i:en>1915-17 Studies at the Teaching and Research Institute for Photography in Munich. Subsequently
                works
                there as a photographer; from 1918 onwards, she runs her own studio for a time. Krull frequents the
                intellectual circles surrounding
                the protagonists and supporters of the Munich Soviet Republic. In 1917,
                her father
                Friedrich Krull passes away.
              </i:en>
            </p>
            <p>
              <i:de>1919 Verhaftung in Österreich mit Willi Budich und Tobias Akselrodt; Überstellung ins Gefängnis nach
                Bayern. Nach der Freilassung politisch motivierte Aufenthalte in Berlin, Ungarn und Österreich. In
                diesem zeitlichen Kontext lernt sie Samuel Levit (genannt Mila, Deckname Kurt Adler) kennen, mit dem sie
                einige Jahre liiert bleibt.
              </i:de>
              <i:en>1919 Arrested in Austria with Willi Budich and Tobias Akselrodt; transferred to prison in
                Bavaria.
                After her release, she spends time in Berlin, Hungary and Austria for political reasons. During
                this
                period, she meets Samuel Levit (known as Mila, alias Kurt Adler), with whom she
                remains in a relationship
                for several years.
              </i:en>
            </p>
            <p>
              <i:de>1920 Ausweisung aus dem Freistaat Bayern aufgrund ihrer politischen Aktivitäten. Umzug nach
                Düsseldorf, ebd. Mitarbeit in einem Fotostudio. Kurzzeitige Mitarbeit in einer Käserei an der
                baden-württembergisch-bayrischen Grenze. Umzug nach Berlin.
              </i:de>
              <i:en>1920 Expulsion from the Free State of Bavaria due to her political activities. Moves to Düsseldorf,
                where she works in a photo studio. Short-term employment in a cheese factory on the
                Baden-Württemberg-Bavarian border. Moves to Berlin.
              </i:en>
            </p>
            <p>
              <i:de>1921-22 Gemeinsame Reise mit Mila nach Sankt Petersburg und Moskau zur III. Internationalen, wo sie
                Lenins Rede beiwohnen; ebd. Verhaftung und Inhaftierung.
              </i:de>
              <i:en>1921-22 Joint trip with Mila to Saint Petersburg and Moscow for the Third International, where they
                attend Lenin's speech; arrest and imprisonment there.
              </i:en>
            </p>
            <p>
              <i:de>1922 Entlassung aus der Haft und Rückkehr nach Berlin; dort Mitarbeit im Fotostudio von Gretel und
                Kurt Hübschmann, über deren Freundeskreis sie auf den (späteren) Filmemacher Joris Ivens trifft.
              </i:de>
              <i:en>1922 Is released from prison and returns to Berlin, where she works in the photography studio of
                Gretel and Kurt Hübschmann. Through their circle of friends, she meets the (later) filmmaker Joris
                Ivens.
              </i:en>
            </p>
            <p>
              <i:de>1925 Umzug mit Joris Ivens nach Amsterdam.</i:de>
              <i:en>1925 Moves to Amsterdam with Joris Ivens.</i:en>
            </p>
            <p>
              <i:de>1926-35 Wohnhaft in Paris; dort als Fotografin tätig, zunächst im Bereich der Mode, ab 1928
                verstärkt im Bereich der Werbe- und Reportagefotografie, u.a. für die Magazine Vu, Jazz und Marianne,
                sowie zahlreiche publizistische Projekte und Fotobücher, darunter Métal, 1928, 100 x Paris, 1929 und
                Études de nu, 1930.
              </i:de>
              <i:en>1926-35 Resides in Paris, where she works as a photographer, initially in the field of fashion, and
                from 1928 onwards increasingly in advertising and reportage photography, including for the magazines Vu,
                Jazz and Marianne, as well as numerous journalistic projects and photo books, including Métal, 1928, 100
                x Paris, 1929 and Études de nu, 1930.
              </i:en>
            </p>
            <p>
              <i:de>1927 Begegnung mit Eli Lotar und Beginn gemeinsamer Arbeit; pragmatische Eheschließung mit Joris
                Ivens für den Erhalt eines niederländischen Passes; Scheidung 1943.
              </i:de>
              <i:en>1927 Meets Eli Lotar and begins working with him; enters into a pragmatic marriage with Joris Ivens
                in order to obtain da Dutch passport; divorces in 1943
              </i:en>
            </p>
            <p>
              <i:de>1928 Teilnahme am Salon de l’Escalier, Théâtre des Champs-Elysées, Paris.</i:de>
              <i:en>1928 Participates in the Salon de l'Escalier, Théâtre des Champs-Elysées, Paris.</i:en>
            </p>
            <p>
              <i:de>1929 Teilnahme an den Ausstellungen Photographie der Gegenwart und Film und Foto (FiFo), Stuttgart.
              </i:de>
              <i:en>1929 Participates in the exhibitions Photographie der Gegenwart und Film und Foto (FiTo), Stuttgart.
              </i:en>
            </p>
            <p>
              <i:de>1930 Teilnahme an der Ausstellung Das Lichtbild, München.</i:de>
              <i:en>1930 Participates in the exhibition Das Lichtbild, München.</i:en>
            </p>
            <p>
              <i:de>1935 Umzug nach Monte-Carlo, wo sie bis 1940 ein Studio betreibt.</i:de>
              <i:en>1935 Moves to Monte-Carlo, where she runs a studio until 1940.</i:en>
            </p>
            <p>
              <i:de>1941 Emigration von Marseille über La Martinique nach Rio de Janeiro.</i:de>
              <i:en>1941 Emigrates from Marseille via La Martinique to Rio de Janeiro.</i:en>
            </p>
            <p>
              <i:de>1942 Anschluss an France libre ebd. u. Ausstellung in der Librairia Franco-Brasileiro.</i:de>
              <i:en>1942 Joins France libre ibid. and exhibition in the Librairia Franco-Brasileiro.</i:en>
            </p>
            <p>
              <i:de>1942-45 Tätigkeit als Fotografin in der französischen Résistance – als Leiterin des
                propagandistischen Fotoservices France libres in Brazzaville, Republik Kongo (September 42- Januar 44)
                sowie in Nordafrika (44) und an verschiedenen Orten der Befreiung in Europa (44 – 45). In dieser Zeit
                verfasst sie Ceux de Brazzaville.
              </i:de>
              <i:en>1942-45 Works as a photographer in the French Resistance - as head of the propaganda photo service
                France libres in Brazzaville, Republic of Congo (September 1942–January 1944) as well as in North Africa
                (1944) and at various liberation sites in Europe (1944–1945). During this time, she writes Ceux de
                Brazzaville.
              </i:en>
            </p>
            <p>
              <i:de>1945 Entsendung als Korrespondentin der Regierung Charles de Gaulles nach Südostasien.</i:de>
              <i:en>1945 Sent to Southeast Asia as a correspondent for Charles de Gaulle's government.</i:en>
            </p>
            <p>
              <i:de>1946 Wohnhaft in Bangkok, Thailand; 1947-66 Miteigentümerin und Managerin des dortigen Oriental
                Hotels.
              </i:de>
              <i:en>1946 Resides in Bangkok, Thailand; 1947-66 co-owner and manager of the Oriental Hotel there.</i:en>
            </p>
            <p>
              <i:de>1948 Tod der Mutter Albertine.</i:de>
              <i:en>1948 Her mother Albertine passes away.</i:en>
            </p>
            <p>
              <i:de>1957 Beendet ihr autofiktionales Werk Chien fou.</i:de>
              <i:en>1957 Completes her autofictional work Chien fou.</i:en>
            </p>
            <p>
              <i:de>1962 Vertrag mit dem Pariser Verlagshaus Gallimard für ein fotografisch ausgerichtetes
                Publikationsprojekt (nicht veröffentlicht).
              </i:de>
              <i:en>1962 Contract with the Paris publishing house Gallimard for a photography-focused publication
                project (not published).
              </i:en>
            </p>
            <p>
              <i:de>1967 Ausstellung im Palais Chaillot / Cinémathèque française, Paris; anschließend Umzug von Thailand
                nach Indien und Anschluss an die tibetische Sakya-Gemeinschaft.
              </i:de>
              <i:en>1967 Exhibition at the Palais Chaillot / Cinémathèque française, Paris; followes by relocation from
                Thailand to India and joining the Tibetan Sakya community.
              </i:en>
            </p>
            <p>
              <i:de>1968 Ausstellung in der Alliance française, New Delhi.</i:de>
              <i:en>1968 Exhibition at the Alliance française, New Delhi.</i:en>
            </p>
            <p>
              <i:de>1976 Beendet ihre Autobiografie Click entre deux guerres.</i:de>
              <i:en>1976 Finishes her autobiograhpy Click entre deux guerres.</i:en>
            </p>
            <p>
              <i:de>1977 Retrospektive im Rheinischen Landesmuseum, Bonn.</i:de>
              <i:en>1977 Retrospective at the Rheinisches Landesmuseum, Bonn.</i:en>
            </p>
            <p>
              <i:de>1980/81 Beendet ihre Autobiografie La vie mène la danse.</i:de>
              <i:en>1980/81 Finishes her autobiography La vie mène la danse.</i:en>
            </p>
            <p>
              <i:de>1983 Rückkehr nach Deutschland, ins hessische Wetzlar, wo ihre Schwester Berthe lebt.</i:de>
              <i:en>1983 Returns to Germany, to Wetzlar in Hessen, where her sister Berthe lives.</i:en>
            </p>
            <p>
              <i:de>1985 Verstirbt mit 88 Jahren in Wetzlar.</i:de>
              <i:en>1985 Passes away at the age of 88 in Wetzlar.</i:en>
            </p>

          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
    </div>

    <div class="card-deck mt-3 mb-4">
      <div class="card">
        <div class="card-body">
          <p class="card-text">
            <i:de>Abbildungen © Nachlass Germaine Krull, Museum Folkwang, Essen</i:de>
            <i:en>Pictures © Estate Germaine Krull, Museum Folkwang, Essen</i:en>
          </p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </div>

  </section>

</MyCoReWebPage>